<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Podcast Notes | Learn and Grow</title>
    <link>/podcasts/</link>
      <atom:link href="/podcasts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Podcast Notes</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language>
    <image>
      <url>img/map[gravatar:%!s(bool=false) shape:circle]</url>
      <title>Podcast Notes</title>
      <link>/podcasts/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Mindscape Episode: Quassim Cassam Intellectual Vices</title>
      <link>/podcasts/mindscape1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/podcasts/mindscape1/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;div id=&#34;podcast-links-and-description&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Podcast Links and description&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Podcast Name: Mindscape with Sean Carroll&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.preposterousuniverse.com/podcast/2019/08/26/61-quassim-cassam-on-intellectual-vices-and-what-to-do-about-them/&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://www.preposterousuniverse.com/podcast/2019/08/26/61-quassim-cassam-on-intellectual-vices-and-what-to-do-about-them/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Apple podcast app&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Date listened: August 29, 2019&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;some-notes-from-the-interview&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Some notes from the Interview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Epistemiology: A subject that deals with philosophical study of knowledge. It deals with what it is to truly know something, sources of knowledge and uses contrived examples to address the problems we are facing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Vices are personal characteristics ; one person may have while others may not. Some vices takes the form of personal traits like closedmindedness, others like wishful thinking, prejudices etc..&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are personal intellectual qualities and there are perosnal intellectual qualities for which we can be criticized…that’s the basic notion of intellectual vices.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our personal traits can be revised, and we don’t always have to be the victim of our characters. The question is how easy would it be to revise personal traits.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For exmaple: A young Tailban man who has a lot of prejudices against women thinks these because of the community and circumstances and might be hard to change. When we are criticizing his attitudes towards women, are we criticizing him or his attitudes? Sometimes its hard to separate this issue.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Overconfidence is catastrophic when it comes to war and military planning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Attitudes, characteristics, personality traits and conginitive bias actively get in the way of truth.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In 1973 Israel received reports of attack from Egypt and Syria, but they strongly believed Arabs wouldn’t attack. The attack did happen. Here the vice is closed mindedness. Commander’s mind was not willing to listen to other point of view of possible attacks from Egypt and Syria.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lesson here is we should force ourselves to think alternatives and be open minded.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Operation babarosa: When Nazis invaded Russia, Stallion believed they would not attack regardless of multiple reports. An example of closedmindedness.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Its possible to have too much of something and we should draw line between open mindedness and closed mindedness&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the end the world turns apparent and we see flaws in our thinking.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Conspiracy theory are the forms of political propoganda and are created to advance your confirmation bias&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We are bad at detecting intellectual vices in ourselves but good at detecting in others&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be honest with ourselves, our thinking styles and zoom into our thought process and look at things that we are willing to recognize vs. not willing to recognize.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Recognize degrees of wishful thinking&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We need to talk more about these intellectual vices and people will start self-correcting themselves.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dr. Cornel West in Joe Rogan Experience</title>
      <link>/podcasts/cornel-west/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/podcasts/cornel-west/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;div id=&#34;podcast-links-and-description&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Podcast Links and description&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Podcast Name: Joe Rogan Experience&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ViWvAnvT17c&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ViWvAnvT17c&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Apple podcast app&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Date listened: August 11, 2019&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;some-notes-from-the-interview&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Some notes from the Interview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anton Chekhov’s short story (best one is &lt;em&gt;Student&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cornel West is author of “Race Matters”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deep comedy: Recognition of mind and soul at deeper level&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is dramatic level of incongruity at the highest level of humanity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Socrates never shed tears: The founder of philosophy in modern west loves wisdom but not human beings. Its impossible to love humans and not shed tears&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can never get full scale variety of human conditions in one confined tradition&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trump’s been able to get away with things with no accountability up until presidency&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trump was able to expose the pre-packaged commodity called politicians&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;America’s sin was not only slavery but the failure to co-exist with indigneous people. They were destroyed through genocide&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wald whitmen, Hellen keller, John Doe, Martin Luther king etc.. all have some grounds of democratic socialism.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The idea of democratic socialism hasn’t been implemented correctly before.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The discourse of whiteness, blackness or brownness is deeply rooted in American laws and rules. Music, art and creative activities help remove the structural barriers between people of different colors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Let the market decide philosophy doesn’t care about ethics and humanity. That doesn’t mean we need to eliminate system; rather ethics and humanity should be the priorities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Democratic capitalism with no accountability breeds a system filled with gross inequality among people&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Its not about symbolic representation only; its about the fundamental transformation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Primacy of morality and ethics create vision to connect as human beings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Moments are not to be trashed; those moments constitute of memory that show what it could be.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Democratic revitalization of the generation: We all have our fears, insecurities and anxiety, we need to be grateful for the love we received. Spread love and justice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Study prior greats in your field; For eg. if you are in statistics, study the best statistician of all time, and see their greatness in the work they did; not to copy their work but to see the greatness and be inspired by them&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Richard Prior, the freest man in 21st century&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Malcom X: A sincere human bein who is willing to update world views based on facts and deep understanding&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Self-giving and self-emptying through arts,music, kindness, sweetness and gentleness&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Oligarchy in music industry controls sentiments of the entire industry.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Social media, spectacle etc.. dilutes gentleness of music&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gary Klark Jr&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Great music goes through your whole body: its like a drug; it changes your state&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dr.Eric Topol on How AI can improve the doctor patient Relationship</title>
      <link>/podcasts/2020-03-11-ai-doctor-patient-relationship/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/podcasts/2020-03-11-ai-doctor-patient-relationship/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;div id=&#34;podcast-links-and-description&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Podcast Links and description&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Podcast Name: Clear and vivid with Alan alda&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.stitcher.com/podcast/clear-vivid-with-alan-alda/e/62737699?autoplay=true&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://www.stitcher.com/podcast/clear-vivid-with-alan-alda/e/62737699?autoplay=true&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Apple podcast app&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Date listened: July 27, 2019&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;notes-from-the-interview&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Notes from the interview:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AI can help doctors free their time:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Physicians are burned out in their work often&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2/3 of doctors activity get focused on typing at the keyboard…wastes time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use voice from AI instead of keyboards and saves time for patient-doctor interaction&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Idea of deep medicine: More deeply we understand a patient’s data, the better we will be to respond to their health issues individually.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deep phenotyping: Characterizing patient in many different layers eg: anatomy trhough skin, physiology through sensors, environment through sensors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AI collects all phenotyping data about the person and helps diagnosis of diseases like UTIs,skin rashes, skin cancer,ear infection accurately.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You don’t need to see doctor for the diagnosis of simple diseases. Lots of routine things which are not of serious nature will be offloaded to patients.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Virtual Medical coach: Avatar on smartphone that collects all your health related data like heartbeat, blood pressure, genome and microbiome. It gives feedback about your health on real time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nearest neighbor analysis: Matches people with similar genomes and what worked for them in different treatment situations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AI is a vital part of personalized medicine development&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;In UK, some hospitals have avoided using keyboards and use voice instead&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Danger of AI: Not accurate prediction of health outcomes and needs tons of improvement&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;AI can accurately and effectively recognize images and patterns which could be time consuming for doctors.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>neil-degrasse-joe-rogan</title>
      <link>/podcasts/nei-degrasse-joe-rogan/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/podcasts/nei-degrasse-joe-rogan/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;div id=&#34;podcast-links-and-description&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Podcast Links and description&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Podcast Name: Joe Rogan Experience&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0pmviUS1Zac&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0pmviUS1Zac&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Apple podcast app&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Date listened: September 7, 2019&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;major-points-from-the-interview&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Major points from the Interview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anything that deviates from reality is reality that has been filtered through your senses. Art at its highest form represents that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Starry night painting (Vincent Van Gogh)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Paul Revere is household name but other war generals go unnoticed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Somebody wrote a poem about him and elevated the importance of his mundane job as a messenger.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Road to sainthood from bein an ordinary person is beatification.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;cherry picking of science to deny things like global warming, vaccines etc.. slows down the progress of civilization&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anamolous behavior of water- it expands when the temperature goes below 4 degree celsius unit the freezing point. Frozen ice insulates the bottom of the lake in winter and fishes survive.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dry ice- frozen Co2&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We interpret life based on what our senses are exposed to&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Telescopses need more sunglight to increase their effectiveness&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Astrophysicists are interested in finding out the position and place of our existence in the universe&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Desalinating ocean water for fresh water is costly and may not be worth doing it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can think of hydro and wind power as solar power since they are all connected to sunglight.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tidal energy could be used to produce electricity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Germans invented modern highway System for the operation of their military&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cars should have been electric 100 years ago when electricity was all the rage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tesla’s idea of broadcasting electricity requires enromous amount of energy to move through the air so that we can power something like bulbs etc..&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you move energy trhough the air to power sth, it can kill you and has tons of other unseen health consequences&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Digital privacy could be a huge problem nowadays&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Social media and search engines are tailoring things to our liking and this might deprive us of stumbling onto something that’s different than what you think&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Benjamin Franklin once said: Those who would give up essential Liberty, to purchase a little temporary Safety, deserve neither Liberty nor Safety.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We are sliding towards total monitoring with the premise that its for our safety and security&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;George Orwell book: 1984&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Social media like fb, twitter, instagram are the gatekeepers of our privacy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We carry around our passive listening devices which catch what we are doing everyday in our life&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Aerospace engineering is one of the greatest inventions of mankind&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;dark matter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Part of the thrill is not knowing what it is we are trying to explore.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As the area of our knowledge grows bigger and bigger the perimeter of our ignorance also grows accordingly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;letters from Astrophysicist, a new book by Neil Degrasse Tyson&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Science can describe how gravity works but can they describe why gravity works&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I can answer your why question most of the time but there comes a point when we can’t answer why question&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spooky action at a distance: Newton&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Einstein defined gravity as the curvature of space and time and you moving in that curvature&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Matter tells space how to curve and space tells matter how to move&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We can deterime the mass of the blackhole based on how fast the stars are moving based on the distance from the blackhole&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
